Guide to the Ben Rosen Papers, 1936-2006 and undated, bulk 1945-1991
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Ben Rosen papers 1936-2006 and undated, bulk 1945-1991
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Rosen, Ben
65 linear feet Extent: 7500 Items
Ben Rosen is an American graphic designer and visual communications consultant. Rosen worked as a designer for J. Gordon Carr and Associates and the Blaine Thompson Company before founding his own firm, Ben Rosen Associates, in 1952, which specialized in corporate identity programs. Rosen is the author of three books on on graphic design and typography: Type and Typography (1963); The Corporate Search for Visual Identity (1970); and Digital Type Specimens (1991). The Ben Rosen Papers span the years 1936 to 2006, with the bulk of the collection dating from 1945 through 1991, and document Rosen's sixty-year career in graphic design and visual communications consulting. The collection contains materials in a variety of formats, including correspondence, writings, graphic design and printed materials, sketches, presentation boards, photographs, and slides, that document design concepts and programs (corporate logos, letterhead, packaging, industrial design, promotion) Rosen developed, through his firm, Ben Rosen Associates, for clients including American Loose Leaf, CCMI McGraw-Hill, Equitable Life Assurance, Exxon/Esso, Food Fair Stores, IBM, Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center, North American Reinsurance, Philip Morris, Richardson-Vicks, Russ Berrie, and Tishman Realty and Construction. The collection also includes manuscripts and published editions of Rosen's books on graphic design and typography, and touches on several of Rosen's commmemorative projects, including a President Kennedy memorial, a United Nations 20th Anniversary book, and Rosen's submission to the World Trade Center Memorial design competition.
RL.01109
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is restricted.
Photographic negatives are closed to researchers. Consult Research Services regarding the availability of use prints.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Ben Rosen Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2005.
Biographical Note
1920 Oct. 20 Born in Detroit, Mich.
1938 Graduated Cass Technical High School, Detroit, Mich. Enrolled in drawing and painting courses at the Society of Arts and Crafts, Detroit, Mich.
1938-1939 Cranbrook Academy of Art, Bloomfield Hills, Mich.
1939-1941 Pratt Institute, New York, N.Y., program in advertising design
1941-1942 Designer, J. Gordan Carr & Associates
1942 Aug.-1945 Oct. Aerial Motion Picture Photographer for the U.S. Army, stationed primarily in England Co-founded a school of Art and Architecture for servicemen at Chalgrove Air Base in England; taught courses in drawing and design Developed a proposal for the conversion of U.S. air bases into British housing; presented plan before British government ministers
1946-1947 Art Director, Blaine Thompson Company, New York, N.Y.
1948-1953 Freelance designer, J. Gordon Carr and Associates; projects included American Airlines, Benson & Hedges, Pepsi, Shell Oil, Sky Chef Package design, Robert Leonard Studio
1952 Founded Ben Rosen Associates
1952-1953 Studio designer, Alan Berni and Associates
1955 Received New York State Teacher's License in Commercial Art/Package Design Began teaching at the School of Visual Art, New York, N.Y.; developed and taught package design course
1963 Type and Typography published Designed John F. Kennedy memorial document
Late 1960s Lectured at Cooper Union, New York, N.Y.
1970s Lectured at Pratt Phoenix Center, New York, N.Y.
1970 The Corporate Search for Visual Identity published
1975 Relocated Ben Rosen Associates from New York, N.Y. to Ho-Ho-Kus, N. J.
1977-1978 Formed Ritta, Rosen & Arnoldy, a consulting firm that specialized in graphic design and corporate identity
1980s-early 1990s Member, Arts Advisory Board, Bergen Community College
1991 Digital Type Specimens published
1992 Wrote Introduction to a new edition of Jan Tschichold's Treasury of Alphabets and Lettering
2003 Submitted design proposal to the World Trade Center memorial competition
Collection Overview
The Ben Rosen Papers span the years 1936 to 2006, with the bulk of the collection dating from 1945 through 1991, and document Rosen's sixty-year career in graphic design and visual communications consulting. The collection contains materials in a variety of formats, including correspondence, writings, graphic design and printed materials, sketches, presentation boards, photographs, and slides, that document design concepts and programs (corporate logos, letterhead, packaging, industrial design, promotion). Rosen developed corporate visual identity programs and packaging designs, first as an employee of J. Gordon Carr and Associates and the Blaine Thompson Company, and later through his own firm, Ben Rosen Associates, for clients including American Loose Leaf, CCMI McGraw-Hill, Equitable Life Assurance, Exxon/Esso, Food Fair Stores, IBM, Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center, North American Reinsurance, Philip Morris, Richardson-Vicks, Russ Berrie, and Tishman Realty and Construction. The collection also includes manuscripts and published editions of Rosen's books on graphic design and typography: Type and Typography (1963); The Corporate Search for Visual Identity (1970); and Digital Type Specimens (1991); and touches on several of Rosen's commmemorative projects, including a memorial for President John F. Kennedy, a United Nations 20th Anniversary book, and Rosen's submission to the World Trade Center Memorial design competition.
The collection is organized into five series: Personal Files, Writings, Business Files, Client Files, and Photographic Materials. The Personal Files Series includes original student drawings and sketches from Rosen's years at Cranbrook and Pratt, and later artwork; World War II materials, primarily relating to Rosen's proposed plan to the British government for the conversion of U.S. military bases into postwar British housing; and limited biographical material. The Writings Series contains articles on package design and visual communications by Rosen and others; manuscripts, published volumes, and promotional materials for Rosen's books; and unpublished book concepts and manuscripts. The Business Files Series includes administrative records, new business presentations, reference files and scrapbooks of creative output from several advertising and graphic design firms where Rosen was an employee or partner. The Client Files Series consists primarily of visual communications design work for a number of clients, and materials relating to several commemorative projects. The Photographic Materials Series contains negatives, photographs, and slides documenting some of Rosen's designs.
Related Material.
Other materials related to this collection and American graphic design may be found in the Gene Federico Papers and Garrett Orr Papers. For material relating specifically to Philip Morris Company packaging and advertising, consult the J. Walter Thompson Co. Archives Corporation Vertical Files, the J. Walter Thompson Co. Archives Domestic Advertisements Collection. For general material on tobacco advertising, see the Sheldon Sosna Papers and the Liggett & Myers Tobacco Company Records. For additional material on Exxon Corporation promotion and publicity, consult the Edgar Hatcher Papers, and the Louis H. Roddis Papers.
Subject Headings
Rosen, Ben; Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963 -- Death and burial; Ben Rosen Associates (Firm); Blaine Thompson Company (Firm); Advertising -- United States; Advertising executives -- United States; Advertising agencies -- United States; Advertising layout and typography; Advertising -- Brand name products; Advertising -- Cigarettes; Graphic artists -- United States; Graphic design -- United States; Graphic design (Typography) -- United States; American Loose Leaf Company (Firm); McGraw-Hill Publishing Company; Equitable Life Assurance Society of the United States; Exxon Corporation; Food Fair Stores, Inc. (Firm); International Business Machines Corporation; Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center; North American Reinsurance Corp; Philip Morris Incorporated; Richardson-Vicks, Inc. (Firm); Russ Berrie and Company, Inc. (Firm); Tishman Realty and Construction Company, Inc. (Firm); Photographs; Proofs; Sketches; Slides; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History
Contents of Collection
- Personal Files Series, 1936-2006 and undated, (5 boxes)
  Includes original artwork Rosen completed, primarily while a student at Cranbrook Academy and Pratt Institute (sketches, watercolors, charcoals, various design projects). Also contains materials documenting Rosen's service during World War II, primarily related to a proposal designed by Rosen and fellow servicemen to convert U.S. military bases in England into housing for British citizens. Also includes limited biographical material. Arranged alphabetically.
  - Artwork
    - Early Work
      - Cass Technical High School (Box 1)
        - Portrait of Ben Rosen, by classmate Freda Zolzman, 1936 (Box 1)
      - Cranbrook Academy
        - Watercolors, 1938-1939 (Box 1)
      - Pratt Institute (Box 2)
        - Student studies, circa 1940-1941, (7 folders) (Box 2)
    - Later Work
      - Charcoals, 1963-1989, (4 folders) (Box 3)
      - Watercolors
        - Beach at Amagansett, Long Island, 1972 (Box 3)
        - Painted postcard, undated (Box 3)
          Note on back of item reads One of many cards sent to friends, made on vacation trips.
        - Summer at Walled Lake, 1955 (Box 3)
  - Biographical Material
    - Anecdotes, 2006-2007 (Box 4)
      Includes memoirs on Rosen's art/design education and early career in New York; family/children; the redesign of the Shell Oil logo; the Kennedy assassination and the genesis of Rosen's design for a Kennedy memorial document, also in the collection.
    - Award certificates, 1951-1969, (2 folders; 1 folder removed to Box 5) (Box 4)
      Awards from graphic design and packaging industry groups.
    - Biographical sketches and résumés, 1960-1970s and undated (Box 4)
    - Correspondence
      - Professional, 1974 and undated (Box 4)
      - Truman, Harry S., 1971 (Box 4)
        Copy of a note from Rosen and reply from the former President.
    - New York State Teacher's License for commercial art, 1955 (Box 4)
    - Résumés--other people, circa 1974 and undated (Box 4)
      Includes drafts of résumés from Rosen's son, Ralph, and from Theodore Toole.
    - World War II materials
      - Air base housing conversion program
        - Clippings, 1945 and undated, (2 folders; 1 folder removed to Box 5) (Box 4)
        - Correspondence, 1945-1946, (2 folders) (Box 4)
        - Photographs, 1928 and 1944 (Box 4)
        - Presentation, circa 1945 (Box 4)
      - Red Cross poster submission, undated (Box 5)
- Writings Series, 1960-1999 and undated, (9 boxes)
  Includes articles and books by Rosen on package design and typography, along with industry reviews of Rosen's design work. Bulk of series is comprised of published book manuscripts, drafts, research, correspondence, and accompanying promotional brochures and reviews for three books by Rosen: The Corporate Search for Visual Identity, Digital Type Specimens, Type & Typography, along with materials relating to the Treasury of Alphabets by Jan Tschichold, for which Rosen wrote the introduction. Also contains unpublished book concepts for two illustrated children's books, a graphic design project on visual identification, and teaching materials on package design and typography. Arranged alphabetically.
  - Articles
    - By Others
      - Graphics Men Pick Best Packages, Printers' Ink, 1960 Nov. (Box 6)
        Profiles Art Crayon package design by Rosen.
      - Package profiles/awards (as featured in Consumer Packaging and American Institute of Graphic Arts publication), 1960 (Box 6)
      - RR & A: Specialists in Corporate Identity and Graphic Design, Commerce magazine (published by the Chamber of Commerce and Industry of Northern New Jersey), 1979 Mar. (Box 6)
        Profile of design firm Rita, Rosen & Arnoldy (RR & A), at which Ben Rosen was a principal.
      - Various short articles featuring Rosen-designed packaging, 1961 and undated (Box 6)
    - By Rosen
      - Attractive Packaging and Display Can Blaze a Trail to Bigger Sales, Home & Garden, 1961 Sept. (Box 6)
      - Contemporary Packaging Termed Inept in Face of Technological Advancements, Food & Drug Packaging, 1962 May (Box 6)
      - Ecology article (environmental responsibility, climate change, lifestyle/policy reform), circa 1970s (Box 6)
      - How Can Deceptive Packaging Be Controlled Or Eliminated? Part of Sounding Board editorial feature, Modern Packaging, 1961 Oct. (Box 6)
      - How Inside-Out Merchandising Affects Hardware, Hardware/Housewares, 1961 Feb. (photocopy, original in Box 5) (Box 6)
      - Lettering and Type Trends, review of Mortimer Leach, Letter Design in the Graphic Arts, circa 1960 (Box 6)
      - PRG (Public Relations Graphics): New Directions in Graphics, Graphic Directions (Art Directors Club meeting, Denver), 1965 Apr. (Box 6)
      - Task of Selection of Design Firm for Exxon Marketing/Identification Review, draft, undated (Box 6)
      - Too Many Manufacturers Make Packaging Errors, Food Field Reporter, 1961 Aug. 14 (photocopy, original in Box 5) (Box 6)
      - Typography in Packaging, Modern Packaging Encyclopedia, 1965 (Box 6)
  - Books
    - Published Work
      - General (Box 7)
        - Copy fitting and marking techniques, undated (Box 7)
        - Expenses, 1989-1990 (Box 7)
        - Promotion, 1990-1992 and undated, (2 folders) (Box 7)
        - Proposed 10-point marketing program for computer-oriented books, 1991 (Box 7)
        - Publisher questionnaires, 1988 and undated (Box 7)
        - Releases, 1990 (Box 7)
        - Royalties, 1967-1999, (2 folders) (Box 7)
        - Van Nostrand Reinhold--Problems, 1990 (Box 7)
      - Corporate Search for Visual Identity (Box 8)
        - Contract, 1966-1967 and undated (Box 8)
        - Correspondence, 1966-1970, (3 folders) (Box 8)
        - Edits and corrections, undated (Box 8)
        - Manuscripts
          - First draft and concept notes, undated (Box 8)
          - Original version, 1969, (2 folders) (Box 8)
        - Promotion, 1970 and undated (Box 8)
        - Published first edition, 1970 (Box 8)
        - Research (Box 9)
          - Articles, undated (Box 9)
          - Interviews, 1966-1969, (15 folders) (Box 9)
          - Notes and additions, undated (Box 9)
          - Preliminary research, undated (Box 9)
          - Questionnaire, undated (Box 9)
        - Reviews, 1970-1971, (2 folders) (Box 9)
      - Digital Type Specimens
        - Books sent, 1990-1991 (Box 9)
        - Copy for text showing, undated (Box 9)
        - Correspondence, 1990 (Box 9)
        - Edits, 1990 and undated (Box 9)
        - Equipment pictures, 1988-1989 (Box 9)
        - Fonts, undated, (6 folders) (Box 10)
        - Manuscript drafts, 1990 and undated (Box 10)
        - Miscellany to include, undated (Box 10)
        - Outline, undated (Box 10)
        - Promotion, Van Nostrand Reinhold, 1992 (Box 10)
        - Published first edition, 1991 (Box 10)
      - Small Commercial Buildings, Richard Snibbe, 1956 (Book design credited to Rosen) (Box 10)
      - Treasury of Alphabets and Lettering, Jan Tschichold (Introduction by Ben Rosen) (Box 11)
        - Drafts of Introduction, 1989-1991 (Box 11)
        - Proofs, 1992 (Box 11)
        - Proposal and contract, 1988-1990 (Box 11)
        - Published edition, 1992 (Box 11)
      - Type and Typography
        - Contract, 1960-1963 (Box 11)
        - Correspondence, 1958-1964
          - Letters to and from contributors, 1962-1963, (2 folders) (Box 11)
          - Letters to and from foundries, 1958-1963, (2 folders) (Box 11)
          - Letters to Reinhold, 1958-1963 (Box 11)
          - Letters to specialists, 1962-1963 (Box 11)
          - Lists of contributors, 1962-1963 (Box 11)
        - Manuscript drafts, 1963 and undated, (7 folders; 1 folder removed to Box 13) (Box 11)
        - Notes and references, 1963 and undated (Box 11)
        - Outline, 1963 and undated (Box 11)
        - Production matters
          - Estimates, 1962 and undated (Box 11)
          - Face lists and space allocations, undated (Box 11)
          - Formatting, undated (Box 11)
          - Proofreader marks, undated (Box 12)
          - Record of included typefaces and sources, undated (Box 12)
          - Specifications and production costs, 1958-1960 and undated (Box 12)
        - Promotional materials, undated, (4 folders; 1 folder removed to Box 13) (Box 12)
        - Published edition, 1963 (Box 12)
        - Reprint authorizations, 1962-1963 (Box 12)
        - Research
          - Artwork/prints, 1963 and undated (Box 12)
          - Lists of type faces, undated (Box 12)
          - Sources for illustrations, Braille, etc., 1963 and undated (Box 12)
          - Text copy sources, 1963 and undated (Box 12)
          - Type designers, undated (Box 12)
          - Type lists, early selections, 1957-1960 and undated (Box 12)
    - Unpublished and abandoned projects
      - Industry books
        - Visual Identification book, (corporate identification as a marketing tool)
          - Notes, circa early 1980s (Box 12)
          - Outline, circa early 1980s (Box 12)
          - Proposal, 1987, (2 folders) (Box 12)
          - Storyboard for television program proposal, undated (Box 13)
      - Children's books
        - Alphabet book, notes and sketches, 1970 (Box 13)
        - Moustache book, notes and sketches, 1970 (Box 14)
  - Teaching materials
    - Package Design course, syllabus/correspondence, 1955, 1966 and undated (Box 14)
    - Reference materials, 1945-1989, (2 folders) (Box 14)
    - Teaching guide, Lettering and Type Style Package, 1985-1992 and undated, (2 folders) (Box 14)
- Business Files Series, 1946-1995 and undated, (9 boxes)
  Includes correspondence, administrative files, new business presentations, reference materials, and scrapbooks of creative examples. Firms represented include Ben Rosen Associates, Ben Rosen Designer, and the Blaine Thompson Company. Arranged alphabetically.
  Some large format materials have been removed from their original locations in the collection and placed in Box 22. A dummy folder, indicated by a title in brackets, has been inserted in the logical location to indicate removal of the item.
  - Ben Rosen Associates
    - Administrative (Box 14)
      - Brochures, undated, (2 folders) (Box 14)
        Includes examples of brochures for Ritta, Rosen & Arnoldy firm
      - Business plan, 1970 and undated (Box 14)
      - Control book of publicity and business mailings, 1972 (Box 14)
      - Correspondence, 1971-1975 (Box 14)
      - [House promotional brochure designs, undated; removed to Box 22.] (Box 14)
      - Newsletter, Corporate Identity, 1969-1972 (Box 14)
      - [New office announcement, Soirée, undated; removed to Box 22.] (Box 14)
      - Publicity program, 1970-1982 (Box 14)
      - Regulations and benefits, 1970 (Box 14)
      - Reorganization plan, 1971 (Box 14)
      - Reports, presentations, speeches
        - Address to the Graphic Design class at Herron Art School, undated (Box 14)
        - Address to the Haworth Men's Club, undated (Box 14)
        - Notes on Purchasing Club Plan, undated (Box 14)
        - Presentation on Exxon Office Systems, 1981 (Box 14)
        - Supplementary recommendations for International Check Systems, 1969 (Box 14)
        - Visual Communications Center, undated (Box 15)
        - Miscellaneous short speeches, 1964-1987 (Box 15)
      - UPC/Postal bar codes and documentation, 1986 and undated (Box 15)
    - Joint project with Paul Arthur, 1981-1983 and undated, (4 folders) (Box 15)
    - New business proposals
      - Bergen Community College, 1995 (Box 15)
      - CCMI/McGraw-Hill, 1984 (Box 15)
      - Exxon, 1977 (Box 15)
      - Joint venture with Stewart & Morrison, 1970-1971 (Box 15)
      - N.J. Typesetting Co., 1980 (Box 15)
      - Port Authority of New York & New Jersey, signage proposal, 1980-1986, (1-4 of 6 folders) (Box 15)
      - Port Authority of New York & New Jersey, signage proposal, 1980-1986, (5-6 of 6 folders) (Box 16)
      - United States Food and Drug Administration, food package labeling format proposal, 1979 (Box 16)
      - Venture calendar/planner design, 2001-2002, (4 folders; 1 folder removed to Box 22.) (Box 16)
      - Other proposals, drafts and letters, 1969-1983 and undated, (2 folders) (Box 16)
    - Outside proposals, 1967-1984, (2 folders) (Box 16)
    - Paper and cover stock samples, 2001 and undated (Box 17)
    - [Publication, What in the World is Packaging All About? 1955; removed to Box 22.] (Box 17)
    - Reference files
      - Capability reports, 1971-1977 (Box 17)
      - How To design manuals, 1966 and undated (Box 17)
      - Other designers' work
        - Bass, Saul
          - AT&T corporate identity program, undated (Box 17)
          - Celanese Corporation, Manual of Style, undated (Box 17)
        - Beall, Lester, Connecticut General style book, undated (Box 17)
        - Canadian National Signs Manual, undated (Box 17)
        - Elanco, Don, Preliminary Corporate Identity Guidelines, undated (Box 17)
        - Lionni, Leo, Olivetti designs, 1952 (Box 17)
        - National Association of Realtors, Realtor Identification and Communications Standards Manual, 1973 (Box 17)
        - Olivetti, A Contemporary Image of Style and Industry, 1962 (Box 17)
        - Rand, Paul, Westinghouse designs, 1961-1968 and undated (Box 17)
        - Richardson-Vicks, Corporate Identification Standards Manual, undated (Box 17)
        - [Stoudard, Paul, calligraphy examples, undated; removed to Box 22.] (Box 17)
        - Union Carbide, Identification Manual, 1965 (Box 17)
        - Varian Instrument Group, Identity Standards Manual, undated (Box 18)
  - Ben Rosen, Designer
    - Early freelance projects
      - Book covers, circa late 1940s (Box 19)
      - Brochures and mailings
        - Ben Rosen Designer, undated (Box 19)
        - Contemporary Graphics, undated (Box 19)
      - Other designs, circa 1948-1952, (2 folders; 1 folder removed to Box 22.) (Box 19)
        Includes work for America's Future, Inc., CHARM magazine, C.J. Herrick & Associates, Fabric Finishing Co., House Beautiful, and Sargent paints.
    - World Trade Center Memorial design competition, 2003-2004, (1-4 of 9 folders) (Box 19)
    - World Trade Center Memorial design competition, 2003-2004 (continued), (5-9 of 9 folders) (Box 20)
  - Blaine Thompson Company
    - Advertisement proofs (Box 20)
      - Celotex Corporation, Acousti-Celotex sound conditioning, 1948 (Box 20)
      - Facing Tile Institute, circa 1947-1948 (Box 20)
      - Ingersoll-Rand Company (pumps, drills, compressors), circa 1947-1948 (Box 20)
      - Sales Affiliates, Inc., (Zotos Machineless Permanent Wave hair treatment), 1940s (Box 20)
    - Brochures
      - American Export Lines, menu concepts, circa 1947-1948 (Box 20)
      - Walter Haeger rental brochure, circa 1947 (Box 20)
  - Scrapbooks and collected work
    - Business cards, undated (Box 21)